<?xml version="1.0" ?>
  <rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
      <title>IngestThis</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com</link>
      <description>Articles, tutorials, and resources for Data Engineers, Scientists, Analysts, and Architects.</description>
      <language>en</language>
      <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:50:09 GMT</lastBuildDate>
      <atom:link href="https://ingestthis.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      
    <item>
      <title>What Is Data Modeling? A Complete Guide</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-01-what-is-data-modeling</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-01-what-is-data-modeling</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[Every database, data warehouse, and data lakehouse starts with the same question: how should this data be organized? Data modeling answers that question by creating a structured blueprint of your data — what it contains, how it relates, and what it means.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conceptual, Logical, and Physical Data Models Explained</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-02-types-of-data-models</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-02-types-of-data-models</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[Most data teams jump straight from a stakeholder request to creating database tables. They skip the planning steps that prevent misalignment, redundancy, and rework. The result: tables that make sense to the engineer who built them but confuse everyone else.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Star Schema vs. Snowflake Schema: When to Use Each</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-03-star-schema-vs-snowflake</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-03-star-schema-vs-snowflake</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[Both star schemas and snowflake schemas are dimensional models. They both organize data into fact tables (measurable events) and dimension tables (context about those events). The difference is how they structure the dimensions.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Modeling for the Lakehouse: What Changes</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-04-data-modeling-lakehouse</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-04-data-modeling-lakehouse</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[Traditional data modeling assumed you controlled the database. You defined schemas up front, enforced foreign keys at write time, and optimized with indexes. The lakehouse changes every one of those assumptions.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimensional Modeling: Facts, Dimensions, and Grains</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-05-dimensional-modeling</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-05-dimensional-modeling</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[Dimensional modeling is the most widely used approach for organizing analytics data. Developed by Ralph Kimball, it structures data into two types of tables: facts (what happened) and dimensions (the context around what happened). The technique optimizes for query speed and business readability, not for storage efficiency or transactional integrity.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slowly Changing Dimensions: Types 1-3 with Examples</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-06-slowly-changing-dimensions</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-06-slowly-changing-dimensions</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[Dimensions change. A customer moves cities. A product gets reclassified. An employee changes departments. How your data model handles these changes determines whether your historical reports are accurate or misleading.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Modeling for Analytics: Optimize for Queries, Not Transactions</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-07-data-modeling-for-analytics</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-07-data-modeling-for-analytics</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[The data model that runs your production application is almost never the right model for analytics. Transactional systems are designed for fast writes — inserting orders, updating inventory, processing payments. Analytics systems are designed for fast reads — scanning millions of rows, aggregating across dimensions, filtering by date ranges.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Denormalization: When and Why to Flatten Your Data</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-08-denormalization-when-why</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-08-denormalization-when-why</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[Normalization is the first rule taught in database design. Eliminate redundancy. Store each fact once. Use foreign keys. It's the right rule for transactional systems. And it's the wrong rule for most analytics workloads.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Vault Modeling: Hubs, Links, and Satellites</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-09-data-vault-modeling</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-09-data-vault-modeling</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[Dimensional modeling works well when your source systems are stable and your business questions are predictable. But what happens when sources change constantly, new systems get added every quarter, and regulatory requirements demand a full audit trail of every attribute change?]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Modeling Best Practices: 7 Mistakes to Avoid</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-10-data-modeling-best-practices</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-data_modeling-10-data-modeling-best-practices</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[A bad data model doesn't announce itself. It hides behind slow dashboards, conflicting numbers, confused analysts, and AI agents that generate wrong SQL. By the time someone identifies the model as the root cause, the team has already built dozens of reports on top of it.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Think Like a Data Engineer</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-01-think-like-data-engineer</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-01-think-like-data-engineer</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[The median lifespan of a popular data tool is about three years. The tool you master today may be deprecated or replaced by the time your next project ships. What doesn't change are the principles underneath: how data flows, how systems fail, how contracts between producers and consumers work, and how to decompose messy requirements into clean, maintainable pipelines.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Design Reliable Data Pipelines</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-02-design-data-pipelines</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-02-design-data-pipelines</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[Most pipeline failures aren't caused by bad code. They're caused by no architecture. A script that reads from an API, transforms JSON, and writes to a database works fine on day one. On day ninety it fails at 3 AM because the API changed its response format, and the only way to recover is to rerun the entire pipeline from scratch — hoping that reprocessing three months of data doesn't create duplicates.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Quality Is a Pipeline Problem, Not a Dashboard Problem</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-03-data-quality-first</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-03-data-quality-first</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[When an analyst finds null values in a revenue column, the typical response is to add a calculated field in the BI tool: `IF revenue IS NULL THEN 0`. That "fix" doesn't fix anything. It masks a problem at the source — and every downstream consumer has to independently discover and patch the same issue.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Idempotent Pipelines: Build Once, Run Safely Forever</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-04-idempotent-pipelines</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-04-idempotent-pipelines</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[A pipeline runs, processes 100,000 records, and loads them into the target table. Then it fails on a downstream step. The orchestrator retries the entire job. Now the table has 200,000 records — 100,000 of them duplicates. Revenue reports double. Dashboards misfire. Someone spends the next four hours manually deduplicating records and explaining to stakeholders why the numbers were wrong.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schema Evolution Without Breaking Consumers</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-05-schema-evolution</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-05-schema-evolution</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[A source team renames a column from `user_id` to `customer_id`. Twelve hours later, five dashboards show blank values, two ML pipelines fail, and the data engineering team spends the morning tracing a problem that could have been prevented with one rule: treat your schema like an API.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Batch vs. Streaming: Choose the Right Processing Model</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-06-batch-vs-streaming</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-06-batch-vs-streaming</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA["We need real-time data." This is one of the most expensive sentences in data engineering — because it's rarely true, and implementing it when it's not needed multiplies complexity, cost, and operational burden.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Partition and Organize Data for Performance</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-07-partition-and-organize</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-07-partition-and-organize</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[A table with 500 million rows takes 45 seconds to query. After partitioning it by date, the same query — filtering on a single day — returns in 2 seconds. The SQL didn't change. The data didn't change. The only thing that changed was how the data was organized on disk.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Data Pipelines: What to Validate and When</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-08-testing-data-pipelines</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-08-testing-data-pipelines</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[Ask an application developer how they test their code and they'll describe unit tests, integration tests, CI/CD pipelines, and coverage metrics. Ask a data engineer the same question and the most common answer is: "we check the dashboard."]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pipeline Observability: Know When Things Break</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-09-observability-monitoring</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-09-observability-monitoring</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[An analyst messages you on Slack: "The revenue numbers look wrong. Is the pipeline broken?" You check the orchestrator — all green. You check the target table — data loaded this morning. You check the row count — looks normal. Forty-five minutes later, you discover that a source API returned empty responses for one region, and the pipeline happily loaded zero rows for that region without alerting anyone.]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Engineering Best Practices: The Complete Checklist</title>
      <link>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-10-de-best-practices-checklist</link>
      <guid>https://ingestthis.com/posts/2026/2026-02-19-debp-10-de-best-practices-checklist</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[Best practices documents are easy to write and hard to use. They list principles without context, advice without prioritization, and rules without explaining when to break them. This one is different. It's a practical, tool-agnostic checklist organized by the categories that matter most — with each item tied to a specific outcome.]]></description>
    </item>
    </channel>
  </rss>